2021.
Invocation by Pastor of Man of Baptist Church, Mr. Mark Nichols.
That's probably a heavily father of the praise you, because you're one of the praise, and we thank you all of this community.
We are blessed in so many ways, and all of the blessings come to me.
Father, we ask for guidance and wisdom for these leaders as they meet, and as they lead, and father as they have motives about what's best for the community.
We ask for the community, we ask for blessings home, and I just ask you to give them a discernment.
And we're only in the decisions that ought to be made to better the community.
Oh, no, that's winter hard.
And we just ask you to leave them in a couple of days.
We'll be able to do that direction.
And we'll need to praise the Lord for all that happens as a result of Jesus' name.
Amen.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the Republic for which it stands.
Well, the foundation and the God in the visible political dirty and justice are all.
Let's give them our thanks, gentlemen.
All right, number four, public input or unscheduled personal parishes.
By considering gender staff recommends we approve item 6 through 13.
Second.
Davis?
All right.
Don't go.
Hi.
Sumber?
Is that?
Hi.
I'm 14 Olson Associates Master Service Agreement Work Order.
Work Order number 2021.
Five engineering and support services for utility relocation on a industrial parkway.
And Steve owns a boulevard, Mr. Sean.
Look on me.
He's in a sewer line.
I'm going to play improvements being a trap trail and Steve owns.
As a court order to get those moves.
It is a hundred percent reimburse by OOT.
We get to work done.
They approve it.
We'll pay for materials, labor, put them in and our engineering.
Any questions for Sean on that?
And this is intersection.
the term fight. They're going to be widening and making turn line. There are really
questions that I'm making motion to approve.
Second.
All right.
Thank you.
There are 15 presentations of the city of mind with fiber study. Mr. Tyler Klein, Mr. James
Lifehead, did a study bring fiber into the community and we're going to go in here asking
him to go out there to study with new costs.
He is here tonight to present those costs and answer any questions that we have.
I think there was a, we previously did a survey to see the interest in bringing in fiber
community. There was a huge interest in it. So, this is a good for an update.
Thank you.
It's a pleasure being here this evening.
I'll continue to speak with you.
We prepared this piece of ability to study back in 2013.
I think it was the first time around the city.
It did some updates to it in 2017 and here we are in a few years later.
Unfortunately, your conditions are opportunity for broadband services in the city
in this last eight years.
Pretty much unchanged.
So it seems like if anything's going to happen within the city and the improvements
it's going to have to be through the city.
Unfortunately, you're not alone, though. That's pretty common.
So we prepared this piece of ability.
It's a hundred and sixty-something pages, I think.
So I'll try to live with this 10 to 15 minutes.
I'll take up too much of your time.
And go through a few highlights here.
As far as the table of contents, just a quick overview.
There's an narrative, executive summary.
It goes over all the other subsequent tabs from a conceptual, high-level plan.
Discusses and technologies.
Our construction cost estimates.
We'll call a market analysis.
If you're competitors or incumbents that are out there today,
providing broadband service at the city,
and then a subscriber forecast that forecast was based on demographics
and a survey that tighter in the city
retain another consulting firm.
To conduct a few years ago, it was thought or so.
So that was taken into our forecast as well.
Feedback from the residents and businesses in the financial
performance.
I'm going to project out.
five years, where we're going to break even, and we're going to turn positive, positive cash flow.
Some of these assumptions are going behind the national program, and then a construction timeline.
Multiple exhibits, as well, such as the U.S. census data, and demographics.
Some national reports, some actual construction quotes.
For this region, this part of the state, for both very ill and very mainline, and we'll call a drop of service line.
Installations inside the house, actual material quotes from different suppliers, different types of materials, and same for the electronics.
So all those exhibits are contained, and I believe Totter has a hard copy of this, and can email you this PDF as well.
An opportunity to view an executive summary.
I'll kind of skip through a lot of that right now.
I'll just skip into the part of the state behind the executive summary, and we'll make a circle back with this.
We have time, but different funding options.
All types of federal funds out there right now, or U.S.
will utility service in TIA, giving away the kind of, like, under their bombadays, and the stimulus funds,
and all that was for broadband, rural areas, same thing right now.
There's billions of dollars being handed out.
Unfortunately, you're kind of caught in the middle, where to be eligible from majority of these funds,
you have to be completely unserved, and they define unserved as our existing services.
It's $25 million down, three megabits.
That's barely enough to conduct a business from your house, and certainly not enough to be a stream.
So unfortunately, your funding options are probably limited, but there are some programs that you might be able to go after.
The USDA office is still there.
It might be one of our sources in the community.
So, several different, over-used, different funding programs.
You might take a look at why you guys are important.
Just real high level.
The type of network we're looking at is called a pawn design.
Passive obstacle network.
This is 100% fiber obvious.
So the latest ingredient is technology out there.
You hear a lot of probably about 5G, different wireless technology.
It's usually a great man or place, but nothing is going to outperform or outlive fiber optics.
So it's virtually a limited bandwidth with a wireless system.
You're replacing those electronics about every 5 years, but the fiber went home and so on.
depreciation schedule typically on thyroid cable is 20 to 30 years.
You know, I did a lot of things.
We can have direct connections from your central office.
Only two businesses that they want to dedicate a point of point
or the pond past office on that work.
It's basically all you have one single fiber strand coming out from your central office
to this passive splitter cabinet out in the field.
We'll subdivide your city up in the kind of like a honeycomb design.
All the small or surface areas in everybody.
We'll have a home run fiber back to these splitter cabinets.
So for every one fiber coming from your electronics,
we'll go through a splitter, you know, split 32 ways.
It's sort of a 32-hunter business.
So it's called a pond or a Jeep pond network.
That's what this study meant.
Cost estimates.
When we ran this years ago, surprisingly, it was about $12 million.
It's come down a little bit.
We're estimating about $9 million dollars total right now.
This is to build out 100% of the city with a care fiber optic network.
All the electronics you need, some software, some monitor, and run the system.
And it's based on these customer premise equipment.
The number of subscribers is based on a little over 2,500.
So that comes.
It's not 100% of your office because we don't know.
Everyone's going to subscribe to the city service.
So these costs estimates are based on our subscriber forecast.
How many people will take the city service?
And we estimated that about 6,000 residents of the business.
The program for $2,500, those will subscribe to the city nine million dollars total.
I will say it's the time of our night.
I've looked at this and there are ways to cut this cost back.
We're thinking that we can get this probably below 7 million to 6.1 million.
If the city could utilize some of your existing personnel, if you're in line with,
or whatever that might be, your construction personnel, to maybe construct the drops, the service drops,
and the size of the house.
Maybe those can stop inside installations.
So there's a way to cut that cost out.
These interrupt me.
Any questions?
Well, you run a drop to each house.
But on the initial installation?
Not really.
We've done these designs, both ways, and there's pros and cons.
The advantage is you get an outside third party contractor in there.
And we'll just say we're going to do 100% of the drops from day one.
So when someone wants service, you can quickly turn them up.
And they're not in the contractor.
It's not bouncing around from one side of town to the other.
As people decide, the problem is you have to pay extra for that.
So our customer premise equipment, for example.
Right now is 1.1 million for 2,500.
So we were to construct 100% of those drops from day one,
you can add another million or more to that.
So we're trying to keep the cost down.
That's a good question because some people do like to do 100%
from day one.
This gets into our market analysis and subscriber forecast.
It's kind of a narrative that describes how we came about.
Our subscriber, you know, take rate or projecting rather than just saying
well the national average or area like this is 50% take rate.
We take a much deeper dive into looking into the demographics,
the number of average age per household, number of people per household,
income, all those things.
And last but not least, how many income is our here today,
which are competition, all that factors that are taken right.
And as well as the subscriber forecast, you guys, and already had conditions.
And here's just kind of breakdown.
Just a number of businesses and number of households through talent.
All of these different factors from poverty level to median age,
commute time to work, everything we can think of.
And the number of service providers or competition,
all those give us a factor to increase or decrease the projected state rate.
You know, as average income above poverty level from most partners,
below all of that factors and overall integrity.
And at the end of the day, we are estimating on a residential side,
little over 32% take rate, one third and about twice that 66% of businesses
that subscribe to the service.
And that equates to the 2,500 subscribers over a five year prediction.
But analysis is just to break down all the incumbents that are there today,
different service plans.
And we get to the heart of this and here's your financial forecast.
We're going to break even.
Does this end?
We're going to pay for itself.
Like every project we do, it's negative cash loan.
As we're starting.
You know, we've got all this cash out late to construct it.
You have no real news coming in.
So you're one.
We're looking at the negative cash loan of 576,000.
You're two.
We're getting close to break even and negative 40,000.
You're three.
We're positive now over 200,000.
And after all your expenses, everything we think of additional
savings, vehicles and insurance.
What do you have at five?
At five.
511,000. And it pretty much flat lines from there. So you're actually hitting over 500,000
year for work. This is based on behind this program. That's kind of an income statement.
But in the study, we have all kinds of assumptions that went into that. How many people are
going to hire? If you're wrongly, we had six new staff members and you're five.
You can imagine more subscribers. You have hooked up the more customer service reps and
technicians you need to operate the system.
I have assumed salaries, vehicle expense, insurance, everything we can think of.
How much will it cost to connect to the internet cloud on the revenue side?
We've come up with three different residential plans and that's something that you'll
want to study all the time. You know, it's in the marketing and sales.
But we've come up with a $49.99 service plan that we would recommend somewhere
around $40, $50, would be your lowest plan all the way up to $99 for a platinum service,
which would be big of a thousand megabits per second.
That's as fast as you can get anywhere in the nation.
And the lowest plan would be 25 megabits down three megabits up.
And that's currently the SEC's minimum definition of broadband.
So, in our projections though, and what we've seen when we go back after the fact,
when we do these studies, everybody wants to fast as speed is possible.
But when it comes down to the look back and money talks to the majority of people
will sign up for the least cost plan that you offer.
So, we factor that into your revenues as well.
Well, over a 50% of the people will take that least cost plan that you offer.
James, I'm going to not talk to you.
So, with this infrastructure, we can get a container from the big mouth of you.
Yes, that's correct. This is actually the, you know,
I refer to it as Jeep on earlier.
The latest is XGS on.
It's a symmetrical service.
It will actually offer 10 gigabits per second down and upstream.
So, we would obviously say go to that place.
10 of what?
And you could offer 10 gigabits services to some of your businesses,
if they want to pay for it.
This is also based on, I have assumed depreciation.
But on financing, we've assumed a 4% cost of money.
So, as though you were going out for a long interest line.
And so, keep those construction costs back a little bit.
If we can find some great dollars, even if we pay for a portion of that construction,
you know, this is essentially your worst.
base in there. These are all the assumptions narrative on the end of the form of and of
lead to less than you really have was a construction timeline. This is a can't chart that
we've included in the report. Basically, you know, it seems we've started July 1st, but this
is not going to happen, but it takes us out to April 23, so a little less than two years
a little project. Design and permit and construction. Would you be able to turn on sections
as you get them done? Absolutely. Definitely would want to do that. You may want to go back
to that original state that you had, I think, was broken into service areas of the city in
different parts of the city. You probably want to reference that. Where are you going to get
the most bankrupt, of course, that you've got to come in. And that's exactly what we do. We
put in the core network, your connection to the outside world. We can start to the
service area and get the revenue. How long would it take for the first one to be active? I know
you can't give me an exact time, but yeah, I know it's going to take over six months still, but
in less than 12 months, so it takes a lot to get the connections and everything that you need and
get IP addresses of the construction itself. Would it be expandable to neighboring communities
if we saw fit? We could, definitely. The electronics that we offer you with this
splitting of the signal, and every time you split that signal, we can present the distance.
But just the one or couple of little deep satellite tronics, we'll go about 20 kilometers, which
is over 12 miles. So we easily go out the day one, 12 miles, and all we would have to do
is to add more remote cabinets or electronics out of them. And we could grow that how big.
The one thing I guess you would have to add is eventually those old teeth can handle. I think
it's close to 10,000 subscribers, so you would never relate the after all of those. It's more
of a matter of the distance. What do you try to cover? And then you're a pipe to the outside world.
We have to get a connection through the states, one that system, one where you hear someone
might bad, to get a pipe in, and a lead with a set of one, two, five gigabit circuits, and they
want to see that some redundancy. As your system grows, then you might need to upgrade those circuits.
Now would you put this system on a loop of some kinder?
As much as we can, yes, we will have some redundancy.
We always do that for your connections, the outside world.
So level for your states network, the cable gets cut.
The whole city is not down.
Unfortunately, there's only so much redundancy.
You can build in with your system right here and down.
We're only looking at one really active set of electronics.
So it's not really in the array around the city.
It's a pawn, asset logical network.
But we'll have multiple fiber routes, if you will, coming from those.
So worst case is there is one of those branches,
you know, serves the north-west corner in the city.
It gets cut somewhere.
That particular section of town might be down for a long.
It just depends on where the cable is cut.
This is the latest technology and you can be offering anything in a metropolitan area.
I think we can see today.
James, can you talk about what 3D could do in this world right now?
I don't know if you can.
Yeah, yeah, we're, you know, we just focus on our engineering firm.
There's nothing but broadband until communications.
I'll say 8% of our work right now is fiber control.
It's only because this is what it wants to do.
Wireless systems 5G, we're starting to know where it is, but everyone's still on the 5G.
We're designing these for electric co-ops, small business batteries.
The city of Shinu, Kansas, we've got something over there project.
That was like a 10-year study before they probably work around on there.
It's still building that out.
Let's place Missouri, that city of Houston, Missouri.
I don't know how long about a little differently compared to the budget for the needs.
So Shinu does their own municipal internet, not croquette.
They've already installed up a run, or they've just clunk a city.
Yes, there's a certain amount of town.
So we can offer wireless as well, and can you offer video services over it?
Yes, definitely.
That's a good point, you know, the revenue is that we've estimated in your assume are strictly a 100% broadband.
There's other revenue opportunities that you could look at if you wanted to offer a voice to talk on,
so I'll go to some of the videos, some of those different ways to go about that.
They're already not having to make that huge investment.
Those connections, basically, are kind of a reseller.
For those other services, the problem is is all of the profit that if you will is on the broadband side,
which are in any profit in video.
The reason you might want to consider, possibly, video services, is that, you know, that triple plate term,
you know, if you can offer all three on one bill, it might increase your take rate on the broadband,
and if you can also offer the voice for video services.
You can't count on making a much more profit that isn't even faster than I would have ever trained.
People are building that over the top and streaming, you know, video and we're cutting that cable.
What about, what about home security? Can it be done over as well?
Yes.
And that's in our narrative as well. So, very good point.
That's, you see, AT&T and some others, advertising on TV now and then for smart home technology and home security.
So, definitely something we need to look at this as it's a broadband pipe.
We'll put any time for service over that.
But we got an afternoon, they give anything on that.
This is where the technology is.
And additional revenue is for you.
Would this be a way we can also put cameras around the city for, yes, or police.
Definitely, in fact, West Plains is using theirs.
West Plains has just been kind of slow to build out.
They just, if it could construct a ring around the city, that's kind of their phase one.
And they're utilizing it for their anti-miss system, for their meter ring,
for connecting all the city offices.
And now they're slowly looking at doing one of these palm service areas for residential building out.
So, they're taking it slow.
They're doing some of the construction on their own.
And that was the original study that we looked at.
Some of the savings of Mr. Roundtree and looked at, you know, as far as picking this up, you're AMI.
Or we're losing revenue and they light your side, even water deep detection.
So, there's other ways that you can, and cutting the corridor for the city's own broadband.
And by ever paying for your broadband connection, that's right there.
You can just come right back to the city.
So, Mayor, as you can imagine, some of the things we've talked about,
internally as well with some other municipalities, the benefits are tremendous,
especially around economic development.
We don't have this type of broadband available to all the businesses that we've talked to as of late,
that maybe looking to come into the area.
That's something that would be beneficial that we could offer as well.
As well as thinking about where we're going as a future with just our,
we're going to come to the city, and we're going to come to the city.
people working from home telework and it can be difficult with some of the lower
speeds to be able to get the full communications that you need to work from home and
so this would give all of our citizens the opportunity if they had to build
a network in a telework type scenario. I think it's something we're going to have to
think about achieving one way or the other and if the city has to take the reins and
then lead then it's something we need to be very seriously considered or our
community is going to get left behind. I can say for a fact that 18T has been
contacted several times by myself and it's not happening. I don't know what I'm going to
do. One of those towns that the ROI is not there and if they're not going to
return on their investments then I'm going to do it and I think the only way this
is going to happen is if we do take the reins and take it up and run with it. We go
out and try to recruit businesses and that's one of the first things to ask about is first
they don't want to go about their electric and their water and stuff like that but they ask about
internet. We got rusty with pizza and I know that's one of their concerns because they want
their stores to build a run and run consistent and with this kind of pipe we can do that. I like
the fact that we can do the home security as well because we have a lot of our systems that
are concerned about protecting our house and their homes or their cells but this
will be a way they can do that. I think it's endless what we can do with it and as new technology
comes along fiber can handle it. There's so much more bandwidth on it than anything else so
I like it. I'm interested. I don't know we probably got more things to talk about especially
funding but I think it's something we definitely need to look at. I will send that you did it and
also the report does survey that. Anybody have any more questions. Thank you. I'm 16 staff reports. 17
trustee community announcements 18 adjournments. So move. Thank you. Thank you.